[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet Museum of
hologography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to holotalk for the week of
May 10
1999 Our Guest this week is Sam Savage
and Sam's lead engineer at Lucent
technology at Bell labs and Sam's going
to come on and speak with us a little
bit about how we can run these laser
diodes and Laser diode modules
inexpensively without spending a lot of
money on expensive power supplies to run
these things and not only inexpensively
but more importantly and now that we're
able to do very beautiful Holograms
using these diodes especially the higher
powered ones such as the recent tests
with the 35 milliwatt but also
consistent results this is one of the
things that running the diodes off the
batteries has not been able to provide
us and that's consistent results if
you're running that especially the
higher powered ones where they're
drawing more current and you're running
that diode for several hours to do a
shot well when you get ready to do the
second shot you're not still putting the
same amount of power into that diode and
your exposure time is going to change
it's very difficult to get consistent
results if you're going to run these
higher power diodes off of batteries
unlike the little laser pointers which
seem to run forever on the batteries
so what we're trying to do right now is
get it to the point where we can
inexpensively run them and get
consistent results which means you can
leave that laser diode on 24 hours a day
and every shot that you do with it
you're going to have the same result and
the same exposure time because you're
still feeding the same amount of power
in now you can go out and buy a very
expensive driver I've seen them for over
a thousand dollars to run these things
but we're looking at doing it for maybe
about twenty dollars or thirty dollars
where you can have that something that
you can plug into the wall run your
higher power laser diode module off of
and forget about it so Sam Savage is
going to come on and give us a little
bit of an idea on how to do that and
where we are with that right now now
Hollow talks getting ready to wind down
for the season if you know this is our
second season and will we run the same
season that the television shows do so
we run from the fall until the spring
and when the TV shows go in summer
reruns Hollow talk goes into its reruns
as well so we're looking at basically
the last shows that are coming up now
next week is going to be a special show
I'm already thinking about some
interesting things to do next year with
Holo talk and one of the things that
I've come up with is to do special
holography broadcasts on the Internet to
our overseas friends such as Germany
Spain Japan South American countries and
a number of other different countries
but in their native language so that
their Educators and their students at
the schools are at home if they have an
internet connection they can log on and
they can listen to a special broadcast
specifically for them in their own
language and learn about lasers and
Holograms in the process it's sort of
like a technological evangelism so next
week we're going to do the first
broadcast in this series and it's going
to be going to Columbia South America
and I met a student in one of my
workshops that I ran over Science Center
that I'm involved with over Lehigh
University and I sat down and I spoke
with him and I asked him would you come
in and do some translations and we'll do
a special broadcast for your country
he's from Colombia so we've got a press
release ready we're going to send that
down to the major newspapers in Colombia
let them know through their media
Outlets that the students and Educators
researchers and the general population
can log on and learn about lasers and
Holograms during a special broadcast in
the native language along with English
so Andres Munoz will be in the studio
with me translating what I'm saying into
Spanish for our South American friends
and next year I look forward to doing
quite a few of these broadcasts they
won't be the regular weekly Polo talk
broadcast after this first initial one
next week and we'll have special Pages
for them to go to and we'll just
continue with our regular programming
every week on the regular whole talk
page so I'm really looking forward to
that as well
so let's move on to Sam Savage interview
Sam came into my studio for a workshop
several months ago he was very intrigued
by creating Holograms using the laser
diodes especially after a number of
different people had told him it was
impossible to do and we've been working
together and Sam's been very helpful
working out power requirements for
driving these diodes as you may remember
I tried a number of different
experiments on my own and they worked
okay power supplies to drive the little
walkmans and things like that and just
running a laser and a module directly
off of that and some results turned out
okay some results didn't even turn out
at all but basically what's happening is
Sam has come up with a way to provide
very safe controlled power that's
inexpensive and the whole point of this
is to be able to be just working with
these as easily as we work with a helium
neon laser which is plugging in the wall
turn it on and work with it and you've
pretty much have consistent results
every time you're working with it
especially with the higher power diodes
because they really do pull a lot of
power current out of the batteries that
we use because I'm still I still use the
three 1.5 volt double a batteries but if
I were to work with that and do another
one later on in the evening hours later
I'd have to adjust my exposure times
because there's less power going into
the module so Sam's going to come on the
show and we're going to talk a little
bit about power and slowly but surely we
are working out every detail of making
semiconductor holography a reality and a
viable a viable reality for making
Holograms so here's a quick message from
my studio and after the message is over
we're going to go right into the
interview with Sam Savage will so I will
say thank you for tuning in and I hope
you tune in each and every week for the
rest of the season we probably have
about two or three shows to go and then
we'll be on reruns for the summer but
we'll be back in the fall with brand new
topics brand new guests and you can bet
your bottom dollar some pretty exciting
information to start off that first Holo
talk show in the fall so I'll see you
next week when our special broadcast to
Columbia South America
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you can do this and
much more by attending one of Frankie's
greatest holography workshops from
beginner to Advanced Frank's got a
workshop that's just right for you from
single afternoon evening or weekend
introductory workshops to Wednesday
evening five-week complete courses and
don't forget his newest Workshop laser
pointer holography
located just off the Northeast Extension
of the Pennsylvania Turnpike and
Interstate 78 the studio is a quick
non-stop drive from the New York
Philadelphia and Baltimore Washington DC
areas for more information call the
Studio's toll-free hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information on
attending a Frankie Freitas holography
Workshop today
thank you
hi is this Anne hi this is Frank defrays
how are you hi happy Mother's Day thank
you is Sam in today hold on a second
hello buddy Hi Sam how are you pretty
good but I just rest a little bit how
you doing okay I thought we'd start off
with just uh getting a little bit of
information and what's some of your
thoughts about these diodes and how can
we run these diodes inexpensively
without having to buy very expensive
power supplies well uh if you supply the
power to the data that the data requires
if you have a power supply and this
applying power tool about it is allow it
to filter and to live and right
potential to that dial then it should be
uh it actually cut out the need for
expensive drivers and stuff like that
there's a couple different ways of
running these laser diodes number one is
just buy a raw diode and Supply the
necessary power at the exact
specifications of the diode and the
other way is to buy the laser diode with
the little micro driver inside
and run it off those batteries do you
see one advantage over the other oh yeah
but but yeah uh yeah sure if you if you
buy the diode draw as it is and have a
supply driving that like with your
batteries but the thing about the by
using the diode in a power supply uh the
best thing to use a battery and keep the
power supply on the battery I see
because the batteries you made me after
a while May fluctuate you know the
voltage may drop but it will over time
but with a battery and a in a power
supply we should be doesn't happen to be
that expensive a cheap power supply on a
battery allowing the battery to filter
out that it supplies any kind of noise
that it might be coming from the uh the
power supply so that I've got a filtered
and that that way it's a lot cheaper
than uh if you bought a driver and
everything else and they think he thinks
with the driver and all that whether
that come out to a little bit you know
yeah but still still keeping it way
below what would cost for healing or any
other gas money yeah now the battery
acts as a pretty good filter then right
the battery is an excellent filter you
look at a battery as you look at
electronic capacity and that uh which
will be a filter all the time on that on
the back will be complete but we feel
much better filter than the electrolytic
capacitor but theoretical you can look
at the battery as the electric capacitor
in in a sense of filtering okay
they've got the capacitive asterisk but
it's the same as the battery of the
words if you have a electrolytic
capacitor that that is working but would
just say uh 75 volt but you know only
going to put it across six volts four
volts or five volts or three bone it's
going to charge up the three-fold
although it's got a working capacity of
75. okay it would do the same work at
three logs that it would at 750 the
properties of that capacitor would do
the same thing that would at a lower
voltage now you wouldn't go above that
voltage uh 35 volts equivalent that
would damage the capacitor and so the
thing is with the battery and looking at
electrolytic uh looking at the same as
electric capacitor the
the battery will do the same thing now
doesn't mean it does not mean that you
can uh that you have to charge a battery
if it's 12 volts or six volts so you
don't have to charge it at that rate if
I if you've got a fixed volt battery if
you're going to come I let acid cell
battery is is really is really good for
uh filtering and keeping a good charge
so if you have a 12 volt battery the the
shortest thing the electrolytic if they
develops in other words you don't have
to charge the 12 volt battery at 12 volt
okay you want to go above
you know over threshold but you can go
below that and it will maintain its
charge if that voltage if the voltage
you're charging that and you have a lot
of capacity there and best thing of all
you have the filtering that you need if
you got a power supply uh if you have a
power supply that's linear instead of
you know switching yeah the the although
if you do have a switching power spot if
the battery will filter but I don't
think I would take a chance with it on a
raw diet yeah uh but supplying one of
the modules it would be oh yeah it'll be
fine yeah now here's here's a little
idea I have we have the 35 milliwatt
diode module that we've been running I
did the Holograms off of the uh module
at 4.5 volts
if I went out and I got a six volt
battery and I drained that battery down
so it was below the six volts actually
below 4.5 and then I got one of the
inexpensive Chargers that you can get
for running walkmans and send that into
that battery at 4.5 volts
and then run the module off of that
battery we'd be in pretty good shape
you're saying you need a 4.5 for the the
driver but I would charge the battery a
little bit more than 4.5 because you can
have a drop you have to take care of the
drop will maintain 4.5 okay I can go up
I could go up and have at least half
gold and uh and charge it that way and
that way that would float at the level
you want it to flow that they're like
you want to let it float at 4.5 that's
what it'll do it'll maintain that and
also uh take care of the filtering that
you need now could that charger be left
on that battery continuously sure now
what we kind of do this real real simple
uh we're only getting the real our
Theory and all this other people
understand but if you have a six volt
battery okay and what you could do is
put a six volt lamp at the bulb in
series with that charger and the battery
you can notice the lamp it will be real
bright with this low charge as as the
battery begins to charge the light will
go dimmer and dimmer means there's no
curving pull from the charger to the
battery that's it gets almost out it
will uh you can say it's charged now
would you leave the charger on there or
take it off I would leave it I'll leave
it on because you also now you have you
can always watch the lamp will also
protect it too okay so you can monitor
it monitor the the uh how your batteries
doing by just looking at the last if you
wanted to charge that battery at 4.5
volts you'd get a 4.5 volt lamp right
well you know uh no you can get a you
can still go
that's still going to be yeah that was
six folks yeah that was still you still
get some light from that
now in essence what the battery is going
to do is it's going to filter out any
noise that's coming from from the AC
line right any any well any noise that's
not been power supply that's not a
filter that goes through go see goes
through your uh power supply then you go
what it's going to do the transforming
you're going to either going to step up
or step it down in this case you'll be
stepping it down then it's going to be
they go through a bridge Rectify in most
cases where the rectifier is going to be
changing that to that AC to pulsating DC
now we're not pure DC yet okay and if
your power supply has got filters in
there that's going to smooth out the
best it can be pulsating DC that's
changing from AC to DC but it's actually
changing from AC to pulse a and DC now a
pulsating DC without being filtered to
any kind of circuit is AC
so the pulsation is absorbed by the
output capacitors in the in your in your
power supply now if any noise gets by
that if there's still some Ripple uh
pulsations in that DC well then the
battery will take care of it so it's a
very good filter right now it's now
standing filter and any type of spikes
that would come through the AC line or
any types of slight variations like if
someone in the neighborhood turns their
air conditioner on or the refrigerator
kicks on and off the battery the diode
running off of that six volt battery at
charged at 4.5 volts will actually take
all that out as well it should filter
out they out but because the AC
fluctuates and changes uh what that
means here you they say it's going to
change oh unless you're power supply is
regulated highly regulated I mean if
it's regularly that means it's not going
to go above what you need okay okay but
uh if it's not very good regulated then
you get spikes but you got spike is
going to get out through the on the
outside of power supply yeah but a spike
or a dip and and it's going to be a
thought about the battery now how would
someone hook this up let's say I have
one of the AC to DC converters that we
run the walkmans off of so one of those
that you can buy over at Best Buy or
other electronic or stereo store to run
your cassette decks their portable
walk-ins and they have
the different adjustments for three
volts 4.5 volts 9 volts so let's say we
buy one of those they're relatively
inexpensive maybe about ten dollars we
set that to 4.5 volts we've got our six
volt battery
and we want to put the 4.5 volts into
the 6 volt battery and we want to run
the module off of the battery do we just
take the wires and attach it to the
battery and then take the wires from the
module and also attach that to the
battery sure yes you take your power
supply and put across your batteries yes
your module
what you're doing you're looking at it
as a filter output filter yes but that
battery is what you're yeah just looking
at it without the filter yeah it's
actually acting more as a filter than it
is the supply you're not really the
battery one reason is batteries uh the
main reason batters are using an
electronic circuit not just it's not
just for Reserve power but it's for
filterization oh I see if you got the if
you've got a uh if you got a circuit
that you uh it acts the filter and acts
as a battery back in the backup in case
you lose uh and they see you have an AC
failure or something so if they're
sitting online now some searches
depending on you know how much load you
have and the batteries may not be uh
the matter may be sitting in a circuit
at the reserve not cut in you know yeah
until you get a low voltage discount
away until you get a power outage and
then the batteries uh cutting and but
most cases the batteries are sitting on
the line on the output of the line the
power supply sitting there charging and
filtering
the the fluctuations in the AC and if
you have an inductive load okay the
inductive load that would take care of
the uh the the know it may be coming
from equipment you know there's some of
the uh the equipment can cause your load
equipment can cause noise and also it
filter that out hmm
so this this is looking pretty good and
very inexpensive I only got the whole
look in that we can get into some
they'll have some real elaborate
regulated and all this stuff drivers but
we want since we've gone to the diode
and not dealing with healing Neons
anymore expensive uh well then Holograms
and we're going to go to trying to make
this thing as inexpensive we can with
and everything has to be inexpensive
yeah and we have to make it uh
everybody wants to be able to do it
we can you can go live if you want to
anymore just like uh you can go
you know expensive you want to get but
we can do something that's cheap that
will do the job well I think that's the
round we ought to try to go absolutely
and it's always you can always run the
diode module off of Regular double a
batteries or whatever but the only
problem with that is is the longer that
that diodes on the less voltage is going
into it and you're getting less power as
time goes on you know that could affect
the diet depending on the diet yeah
the battery and say let's say that uh
the battle for the let's say the the
current drain the load of a a 35
millilit a laser diet is set 45
milliamps well then it won't take long
you know too long for uh that you just
put the battery on it without any not
keeping it floating the voltage is going
to drop yeah and the height like the 500
milliwatt that was uh over a thousand a
milliamp because you know you're talking
about uh one amp yeah so you know in a
bag that ain't gonna last long at all I
mean that's so that's going to drop that
won't be enough for the diode and that
could cause uh heating problem to die oh
and if I know what there's no problem
okay he had a pretty good range there on
that five milliwatt corner
when you start getting up into more
power on a dive you know increasing we
call up in power well if if I swear on
you know that's that's uh where you
times that that's going to be more what
it's going to be more current pulling uh
it's gonna require more current to
operate and that's why it's a good idea
to have a battery with a charger sitting
on it and perfectly the uh the lead acid
sound like a lawnmower battery yeah I
used to uh one is the lead acid yeah I'm
not sure about motorcycle batteries I'm
not sure if they're 12 volts or 6 volt
because I think the lawnmower batteries
are like six foot well I think you can
buy you can buy these uh lead acid sales
there's pretty good amp hours on it and
at two volt and you used to be uh maybe
in the bathrooms at 1.5 of them and then
you have a lot to deal with you know you
play with the lead acid a lot of
capacity and enough that expensive uh
see some places around to have it you
can get these and the gates uh makes the
lead acid sell about three inches in
diameter you know about uh six inches
high or something like that it's got
pretty good capacitance lead acid and
you can string them up to the uh the
that you need and put your charge across
them and if you wind up with More
Voltage than you need you can just you
can just drop it you just uh you just
drop yeah figure out your voltage drop
the vote that you need bigger that
voter's job then you're determine that
from your uh the amount of current is
going to be using and then you can
determine uh with those law determine
what kind of resistance you need to drop
that bow now just put a resistor right
in line there right exactly yeah well it
seems pretty easy and like why go out
because I've seen some of the power
supplies for the diodes that are running
over a thousand dollars absolutely the
uh the drivers sometimes they uh
are very expensive but I believe we can
uh we can do it a lot cheaper we made it
so uh inexpensive especially with your
shoebox photography I mean my goodness
and it dropped it uh putting in the cost
that's come way down late he's a long
time what it used to be we made making
history in the making Pioneer we might
as well get like the power supplies
along with the diodes you gotta make it
all cheap so people be able to to do it
yeah you have that hologram to the angel
now what do you think of that that's an
example that is that is actually
breathtaking to know that was taken with
a 35 millilitar diode and a helium they
are I couldn't do a good job of that but
if uh it's really unbelievable actually
I know it's hard for folks to see that
on the internet on a picture I've taken
have you taken a picture of but actually
seeing this hologram uh if it's actually
breathtaking it's unbelievable the depth
with the you know the wings and all that
it's just it's just unbelievable it's
real bright it's amazing that they touch
real bright
uh if it's amazing it really is amazing
well Sam I want to thank you for taking
the time today to come on the show
and don't forget to log on tonight it'll
be on by midnight tonight which is
Sunday and I'll be talking with you I
guess a little bit later in the week
thanks very much Roy I'm glad to be able
I'm not too good at this talking so
special ideas but uh thanks for having
me on all right Sam bye talk to you
later